Finding Aid for Hazel Littlefield Smith Papers ca. 1830s-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hazel Littlefield Smith Papers circa 1830s-1979
Smith, Hazel Littlefield.
5.3 linear feet
Resident in China from Farwell, Michigan; papers concern her family life in Farwell, and missionary activities; include letters, diaries, and accounts of father, Josiah L. Littlefield, Farwell lumber dealer and visitor to China, 1916-1917; letters, 1918-1928, of husband, Dr. Dennis V. Smith, medical missionary to China, describing in part Chinese politics and civil war, 1918-1920; letters and other papers of Hazel Littlefield Smith, including materials concerning various European travels, and manuscripts of writings about Irish author Lord Dunsany, her father, and Farwell, Michigan; and photographs. Other correspondents of Hazel Smith include world-renowed scientists (Edwin Hubble and William Beebe), from Chinese Princess Der Ling, and from distinguished European writers and actors (Pierre LaMure, Selma Lagerlof, Brian Aherne, and Ronald Colman).
85412 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Hazel Littlefield Smith (donor no. 3915 ) and came to the library in several accessions, mainly 1978-1984; additional materials were received from Haldon L. Smith (donor no. 10727 ) in February 2012.
The collection is open for research.
Hazel Littlefield was born in Farwell, Michigan and graduated from the University of Michigan (AB, 1913). In 1913, she married Dennis Vincent Smith who had graduated the previous year with a doctor of medicine degree from the university's medical school. The couple then moved to China where they worked for fourteen years under the Methodist Board of Foreign Missions in Peking, China. Smith was head of the Hopkins Memorial Hospital Eye Department, where he trained Chinese doctors as well as doing eye surgery. The Smiths returned from China in 1928 with Dr. Smith serving as an ophthalmologist at the Battle Creek Sanitarium. They next moved to Long Beach, California where he practiced his specialty for 29 years. They returned to Ann Arbor in 1960, and from 1961 to 1971, he served as an ophthalmologist at the U-M Health Service.
Hazel Littlefield Smith, in addition to her work with the Methodist Church, was also a poet, historian and biographer.
This collection was accumulated by Hazel Littlefield Smith and consists of materials concerning her career and interests and those of her family, specifically her husband, Dr. Dennis Smith, and her father, Josiah Littlefield (1845-1935), a pioneer lumberman and businessman in Farwell, Michigan.
The collection is particularly valuable for three topics: early days (late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries) in Farwell, Michigan; missionary life in China in the period ca. 1915-1928; and the travels and writings of Hazel Littlefield Smith. The materials include correspondence, compositions and business-related materials of Josiah Littlefield; correspondence and other materials of Dr. Dennis Smith, Hazel Littlefield Smith (and Josiah Littlefield) concerning conditions in early republican China; and correspondence and other materials of Hazel Littlefield Smith concerning her travels in Europe (1920s-1950s), her management of the family farm near Farwell, Michigan (1940s), and her essays, poetry and other publications, including Lord Dunsany: King of Dreams.
The three principal figures in the collection--Hazel Littlefield Smith, Dennis Smith and Josiah Littlefield--were highly perceptive observers of persons and events. Their letters are rich in detail, whether describing travel experiences or everyday life in rural northern Michigan.
The collection is arranged into six series: Littlefield Family, China-related materials, Hazel Littlefield Smith, Miscellanea, Dr. Dennis V. Smith, and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1878-1957.; Farwell (Mich.); Logging--Michigan--Farwell.; Lumbering--Michigan--Farwell.; Missionaries, Medical--China.; Physicians--China.; Smith, Hazel Littlefield.; Travelers.; Voyages and travels.; Women--Michigan--Farwell.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Aherne, Brian.; Automobiles--1911-1920.; Automobiles--1921-1930.; Carriages and coaches.; Carts and wagons.; Children.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; China--Missions.; Dining rooms.; Dunsany, Edward John Moreton Drax Plunkett, Baron, 1878-1957.; Dwellings.; Farms--Michigan--Farwell.; Farwell (Mich.); Farwell (Mich.)--Farms.; Farwell (Mich.)--Lumber industry.; Health care.; Hospitals--China.; Interiors.; Littlefield family.; Lumber industry--Michigan--Farwell.; Missionaries--China.; Missions--China.; Smith, Dennis V.; Smith, Hazel Littlefield.; University of Michigan. Class of 1871.; University of Michigan--Alumni and alumnae--Anniversaries, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--1911-1920.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Aherne, Brian.; Der Ling, Princess.; Littlefield, Josiah L. (Josiah Loomis), 1845-1935.; Littlefield family.; Smith, Dennis V.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Diaries.; Glass photonegatives.; Lantern slides.; Photographs.; Stereographs.
- Littlefield Family
  The Littlefield Family series provides biographical and genealogical content relevant to Hazel's childhood. Of particular interest are diaries by Josiah L. Littlefield and Emma L. Littlefield, along with business accounts of the family business in Farwell, Michigan.
  - Genealogical material (Box 1)
    (1-1)
  - Daniel Littlefield (Josiah Littlefield's father) Letter
    (1-2)
    - Letter from B (?) Hall written from Oberlin, Ohio, with comments on life at Oberlin College and describing the attempts by southern slave-catchers to seize a runaway slave named Allen September 27, 1842 (Box 1)
  - Josiah L. Littlefield
    - Papers 1845-1945 (Box 1)
      (includes compositions and addresses, biographical information)
      (1-3)
    - Correspondence 1870-1934 (Box 1)
      (1-4)
    - Travel diaries for railroad trips taken to California in 1920, 1925 (Box 1)
      (l-5)
    - Accounts at the hardware store of M.D. Todd in Farwell,Michigan 1875-1879 (Littlefield was then in business as the proprietor of a planing and shingle mill) (Box 1)
      1-6
    - Account Book 1898 (Box 1)
      1-6a
    - Diaries
      - 1927 1928 (Box 1)
        1-6b
      - 1930 1935 (Box 1)
        1-6c
  - Emma L. Littlefield
    - Diaries 1887-1927 (scattered) (Box 1)
      1-6d
    - Autograph Books
      - 1877 1881 (Box 1)
        1-6e
      - 1884 (Box 1)
        1-6f
  - Pages taken from the account book of the Littlefield general store in Grafton, Mich. 1834-1844, photocopies (Box 1)
    (1-7)
  - Miscellaneous publications (Box 1)
    (l-8)
  - Farwell, Michigan
    - Papers re. the history of Farwell, Michigan (Box 1)
      l-8a
    - Record book of the Farwell City Company 1871-1873 (Box 3)
    - Labor Ledger for Beechwood Lumber Camp 1888-1891 (Box 3)
  - Lecture Book, W.W. Elder undated (Box 3)
  - Accounts of Lucas Cain Jr. 1890-1892 (Box 3)
- China-related materials
  The items found in China related-materials document the years Hazel and her husband Dr. Dennis V. Smith spent in Peking while the latter worked as a surgeon. Most letters in this series are described at the item level. Harvey James Howard's famous work Ten Weeks with Chinese Bandits is represented here under the title "Ten Weeks with the Black Dragon River Bandits," that having been the name when it was first published as a series of newspaper stories in the Peking Leader.
  - Letters of Hazel Littlefield Smith from Peking and Pai tai-ho, China 1915-1927 (Box 1)
    (1-9)
  - Letters of Josiah L. Littlefield written from Peking, China in 1916-1917 (Box 1)
    (One is addressed to the students of Farwell (Mich.) High School and concerns his observations on Chinese Educational institutions. Another is written from Shanghai to the editor of a Clare County newspaper. Six are written from Peking to the editor of the Clare county newspaper. There are also newspaper clippings of some of the articles, containing minor corrections in the texts, and, in one case, only the clipping is here, not the original letter)
    (1-10)
  - Two hand-written diaries kept by Josiah L. Littlefield while in China, containing observations on things he observed, including the new Republic of China's parliament in session (Box 1)
    (1-10a and 1-10b)
  - Josiah L. Littlefield address to a group of Chinese Christian theological students in Peking 1917 (Box 1)
    (1-11)
  - Miscellanea pertaining to the Smiths' stay in China (Box 1)
    (1-12)
  - Account of a trip to Jehol, the summer residence of the emperors of China, ca. 140 miles northeast of Peking, 25 pp (Box 1)
    (1-13)
  - Guest Book, Peking 1917 (Box 1)
    (1-13a)
  - Chit Book (Box 1)
    (1-13b)
  - Cash books 1914-1919 (Box 1)
    (1-13c)
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith en route to China 1915 and from Peking, 1916-1917 describing the activities of the hospital, Christian missionaries, his family and friends, and China's internal politics and civil war (Box 1)
    (include letter describing the "Battle of Peking," fought between forces of the Republic of China on one hand and those favoring restoring the monarchy on the other, July 12, 1917)
    (1-14)
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith from Peking 1918-1921 (Box 1)
    1-14a
  - Chinese Post Cards acquired by Hazel Littlefield Smith 1920-1928 (Box 1)
    1-14b
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith and Hazel Littlefield Smith written while traveling from New York to Peking via Vienna, Cairo, Singapore and Hong Kong 1922 (Box 2)
    (also includes a 10 pp. account by Dr. Dennis Smith of his side trip from Cairo to Jerusalem, ca. 1922)
    (2-14c)
  - Notes by Hazel Littlefield Smith 1923-1925 (Box 2)
    2-14d
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith from Peking 1923-1926 (Box 2)
    (2-15)
  - "Ten Weeks with the Black Dragon River Bandits" by Harvey James Howard 1926 (Box 2)
    2-15a
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith from Peking 1927 (Box 2)
    2-16
  - Order Book 1927-1928 (Box 2)
    2-16a
  - Letters of Dr. Dennis Smith from Peking 1928 (Box 2)
    2-17
  - Dr. Dennis Smith Notes from Diary, China circa 1928 (Box 2)
    (2-17a)
  - Peking January 1915 "Arrival in China" (Box 2)
    2-18
  - Letters undated (Box 2)
    some material in German
    2-18a
  - Clippings re. China and miscellaneous printed item (Box 2)
    (2-19)
  - Typescript: "Boxer Rebellion-Peking" (Box 2)
    (2-20)
  - Dr. Dennis Smith papers, entitled "Young China Seeks Health"; "Some Chinese I have Known"; and "Medicine as a Christian Life Work" (Box 2)
    (2-20a)
- Hazel Littlefield Smith
  The Hazel Littlefield Smith series is divided into four subdivisions, including Early Papers and travels, Writings, Correspondence, and Clippings. Of these, the Correspondence subdivision contains the richest content. Hazel's correspondents included world-renowned scientists (Edwin P. Hubble and William Beebe) distinguished European writers and actors (Pierre LaMure, Selma Lagerlof, Brian Aherne and Ronald Colman), and Chinese Princess Der Ling. Her correspondence with Irish author Lord Dunsany is especially extensive as it reflects their mutual interest in each other's literary careers.
  - Early Papers and travels
    - Early family correspondence (Box 2)
      (2-20b)
    - Autograph Book 1893 (Box 2)
      2-20c
    - Letters, reminiscences concerning her trips to Bohemia and Germany in 1921-1922 (Box 2)
      (2-21)
    - Clippings (mounted) re. a trip by HLS to England around 1936 (Box 2)
      (2-22)
    - Trip to England in the summer of 1939 (Box 2)
      (2-23)
    - An account by HLS of a visit by a young English poet, John Stanley Richardson, who stayed in her Calif. home during 1940 tour of the U.S. (Box 2)
      (also includes a copy of a book of his verse)
      (2-24)
    - Materials (mostly correspondence) related to HLS trip to England and Ireland in 1947 (Box 2)
      (includes her essay "Irish Interlude: Deer Stalk in Donegal, 1947")
      (2-25 and 26)
    - Correspondence and miscellaneous materials pertaining to HLS trip to England, Switzerland and Czechoslovakia in 1949 (Box 2)
      (2-27)
    - Letter pertaining to HLS trip to England in 1957 (Box 2)
      (2-27a)
  - Writings
    - Manuscript for the volume by HLS entitled, "Farwell: The First Fifty Years" (Box 2)
      (2-28)
    - Manuscript (and proofs) of HLS [ed.] "Josiah Littlefield--Lumberman-Conservationist.", 3 folders (Box 2)
      (2-29, 30, 31)
    - Manuscript of HLS, "Lord Dunsany: King of Dreams" (Box 2)
      (2-32)
    - Classroom paper on Lord Dunsany 1965 (Box 2)
      (2-33)
    - Miscellaneous materials re. HLS's book, "Lord Dunsany: King of Dreams." (Box 2)
      (2-34)
    - Miscellaneous memberships, honors, memorabilia (Box 2)
      (2-35)
    - Poetry (Box 2)
      (2-36)
    - Miscellaneous Writings (Box 2)
      (include chapters from autobiography, account of her experience in the 1933 Long Beach, California earthquake, and essay entitled "Lumbering Days")
      (2-36b)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Dennis V. Smith 1911 (Box 2)
      2-37
    - Letters from Brian Aherne to HLS
      - 1958-1965 (Box 2)
        (2-37a)
      - 1966-1972 (Box 2)
        (2-37b)
      - 1973, 1975-1978, undated (Box 2)
        (2-37c)
      - Letters and clippings relating to Brian Aherne 1959-1973 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
        (2-37d)
    - Letters from Chinese Princess Der Ling (Mrs. Elizabeth White) to HLS 1930, 1940 (Box 2)
      (2-37e)
    - Correspondence, including letters, some undated, written to her family from Lochabar, the family home near Farwell, Michigan 1940s (Box 2)
      (2-38)
    - Correspondence and other items 1940s-1970s (Box 2)
      (2-38a)
    - Letters 1905-1970 (scattered and undated) (Box 2)
      2-39
    - Distinguished Correspondents circa 1930s-1979
      - Lord Dunsany (Box 3)
      - B -- H: includes William Beebe, Rev. Thomas Arthur Bold, Lord David Beatty, the Earl, Sir Arthur Wynne Morgan Bryant, CH, CBE, Witter Bynner, Sarah Churchill, Ronald Colman, Lord Dynevor, Bishop George R. Grose, Edwin P. Hubble (Box 3)
      - I -- S: includes Lord Inchiquin, Commander William King, Selma Lagerlof, Pierre LaMure, Shane Leslie, Dr. John Murray, Alfred Noyes, John Stanley Richardson, Sir David John Montagu-Douglas Scott, Captain H. St. Clair Smallwood, O.B.E. (Box 3)
  - Clippings relating to HLS (Box 3)
- Miscellanea
  In the Miscellanea series one will find popular publications and ephemera of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
  - McClure's Magazine, June 1896 (Box 3)
  - The Youth's Companion, 1900-1904 (Box 3)
  - Ethel L. Smither's Primary Stories, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Booklet: "The Chinese Lama Temple Potala of Jehol" (Box 3)
  - "Memories of Frank Murphy," 1965 (Box 3)
  - Play poster 1910 "The Choice" with Frank Murphy and Hazel Littlefield (Box 3)
  - Clippings (Box 3)
- Dr. Dennis V. Smith
  Account books chiefly comprise the Dr. Dennis V. Smith series, spanning the family's stay in China as well as California.
  - Spelling Book 1898-1900 (Box 4)
  - Account books 1904-1961 (some gaps), 39 volumes (Box 4)
    (two volumes also contain the accounts of HLS)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series holds photographs from China and two oversize scrapbooks with illustrations, postcards, and calendars portraying American and Chinese cultures. The photographs are predominantly views of Chinese people, towns, and countryside, and of the Methodist Sanitarium and eye clinic where Dennis Smith served as medical missionary. There are also portraits and photographs of members of the Littlefield family, photos of Farwell, Michigan, and of the Littlefield farm and sawmill near Farwell. Also included are miscellaneous photos of family activities and celebrations and group portraits of reunions of the University of Michigan Class of 1871.
  - Photographs
    - Aherne, Brian (Box 5)
    - China (Box 5)
    - Family; Farwell, Michigan (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Album Trip to Jehol, China, taken by Dr. Richard Smith, 1 volume (Box 5)
    - Albums, 13 small albums (in 1 folder)
      - Pei-Tai-Ho 1915, 2 volumes (Box 5)
      - Legation Street (Box 5)
      - Summer Palace and Temple of Heaven 1916 (Box 5)
      - Tai-Shan 1916 (Box 5)
      - Chinese methods of transportation (Box 5)
      - Peking 1915, 2 volumes (Box 5)
      - Peking 1916 (Box 5)
      - Eye clinic, Methodist Sanitarium (Box 5)
      - Tientsin Flood, Autumn of 1917 (Box 5)
      - The Great Wall; Devil Dance at Lama Temple; Compound Views (Box 5)
      - Chinese life (Box 5)
    - Glass Negatives (family and home; Farwell, Michigan; farming; music; children) (Box 5)
    - Lantern slides: China; Eye Clinic; Methodist Sanitarium, 1 wooden box (Box 5)
    - Pasteboard household gods given to Dr. Dennis Smith in Peking,1916 (Box 5)
      (used by the Smiths' Manchu teacher,Wang HsienShung)
    - Volume: China through the stereoscope by James Ricalton (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook 1920s illustrations of Chinese palaces (Box 6)
    - "Scraps" -- illustrated postcards and calendars reflecting American and Chinese cultures circa 1900 (Box 6)